Register of the Committee for the Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property Records, 1954-1962
Hoover Institution Archives
Committee for the Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property Records,
1954-1962
63002
Committee for the Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property
33 manuscript boxes (13.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Minutes of meetings, reports, correspondence, press releases, position statements, legal briefs, notes, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1963.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Confiscations and contributions.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Germany.; Japan.; United States--Foreign relations.
Historical Note
The Committee for the Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property sought the complete restitution of private German and Japanese property confiscated by the United States Government during and after World War II. Located in Washington, D.C., between April 4, 1954, and December 31, 1962, the Committee distributed information, prepared reports and studies, solicited public support, initiated legislation, and lobbied in Congress for its proposals.
Members of the Committee's executive board were Frederick J. Libby (Chairman), James Finucane (Executive Secretary), Dr. Charles S. Collier, Bishop Wilbur E. Hammaker, Dr. Goetz A. Briefs, Dr. John A. Scherzer, Conrad J. Linke, Mike M. Masaoka, and the Honorable Francis B. Sayre.
Collection Contents
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1954-1962 (Boxes 1-14)
  Correspondence, biographical data, copies of public statements, and legal briefs. A major portion of the correspondence deals with confiscated German property. Correspondence filed under Mike Masaoka, the Washington representative of the Japanese-American Citizens' League, concerns Japanese property. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - A (Box 1)
  - Abs, Herman
  - Adair, E. Ross
  - Adams, Mr. Dinsmore
  - Allen, Devere
  - Ahrens, D. H.
  - American Bar Association
  - American Legion
  - App, Dr. A. J.
  - Arai, Yoneo
  - Arnade, Col. Kurt
  - B-Bl (Box 2)
  - Baade, Dr. Fritz
  - Barnes, Dr. Harry
  - Bauer, Karl
  - Bennett, John B.
  - Bo-Br
  - Boyken & DeFrancis
  - Briefs, Dr. Goetz
  - Bs-
  - Burke, Coleman
  - C
  - Christian Century (Box 3)
  - Christian Herald
  - Collier, Dr. Charles
  - Corcoran, Thomas
  - D
  - Daniels, Richard
  - Davis, Gladys
  - Decker, Emil
  - Deutsch Bank
  - Durholz, Otto
  - E
  - F (Box 4)
  - Farben, I. G.
  - Fischer, Charles
  - German American Chamber of Commerce
  - German Embassy
  - Gerhard, Charles
  - Ginsburg, David
  - General Aniline and Film Corporation
  - Ha
  - Hamburger, Adolf (Box 5)
  - Hammaker, Bishop Wilbur
  - Hand, Judge Learned
  - Harris, Oren
  - He-Hu
  - Hruska, Senator Roman
  - I
  - Inquiry, letters of
  - J
  - Johnston, Senator Olin
  - K (Box 6)
  - Kade, Max
  - Kennedy, John F.
  - Klein, General Julius
  - Klepinger, Robert F.
  - Klinedinst, David M.
  - Kunster, Mrs. Ingeborg
  - L
  - Lange & Springer
  - Langer (Box 7)
  - Laun, Rudolph
  - Leutz, Dr. Gretel
  - Libby, Frederick J.
  - Lichtenfels, William
  - Linke, Conrad
  - Littauer, Rudolph
  - M
  - Mack, Peter F. (Box 8)
  - Masaoka, Mike
  - Michler, Gordon
  - Miller, Paul
  - Mc-Mac
  - N
  - National Association of Manufacturers
  - National Council of Churches
  - New York Times
  - O
  - Oppenheimer, Fritz
  - Pa-Pe
  - Pf-Pz (Box 9)
  - Pearson Column
  - Pearson, Collier
  - Perry, Mr. Henry
  - Peter, Bernard
  - Pfund, Dr. Harry
  - Phillips, E. Gordon
  - Public Affairs Committee
  - Q
  - R-Re
  - Rh-
  - Robert, Jon, Jr.
  - Roehrich, Gertrude
  - Roosevelt, Mrs. Franklin D.
  - Rosden, George (Box 10)
  - Rubin, Seymour
  - S
  - Saint Louis Post
  - Sayre, Honorable Francis
  - Scattergood, Mrs. Margaret
  - Scherzer, Reverend John
  - Schuchardt, Irmgard
  - Schutte, Dr. Ehrenfried
  - Shearmen & Sterling (Box 11)
  - Shore, Chester
  - Sims, Cecil
  - Smathers, Senator George
  - Social Action
  - Staats, Zietung
  - Stinnes, Edmund
  - Stinnes, Otto
  - Studiengesellschaft fur Privatrechtlicke Auslandsinteressen
  - T (Box 12)
  - Thiesling, Dr. Theo H.
  - Tittmann, Charles
  - Token, William
  - U
  - U.S. Government
    - Budget, Bureau of
    - Congressional Library
    - Foreign Claims Commission
    - Justice, Department of
    - State, Department of
    - White House
    - Miscellaneous
  - V (Box 13)
  - Von Clemm, Werner
  - W
  - Wall Street Journal
  - Washington Post & Times Herald
  - Watches
  - Wehrli, Edmund (Box 14)
  - Wilson, John, Jr.
  - Wirsing, Hans
  - Wohthat, Helmuth
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom
  - Wright, Professor Quincy
  - X, Y, Z
  - Unfiled Correspondence
- SUBJECT FILE, 1955-1962 (Boxes 14-22)
  Reports, memoranda, press releases, correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings, and printed matter. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Administration bill. Copyrights, Congressional Record excerpts (Box 14)
  - Administrative proposal. Newspaper clippings (German and English), notes, correspondence and basic documents; includes government documents which were prepared and distributed to subscribers of "Confiscated Property Information Services", the publication of the Committee for Return, 1955
  - Administrative proposal. Newspaper clippings, notes, and correspondence; includes an analysis of the War Claims Act Amendments submitted by the Foreign Claims Settlement Commission in Behalf of the Executive Branch, 1958 July 8
  - American Council on Germany. Correspondence, minutes and drafts of charters relating to the establishment of the Council
  - Bayer vs. Sterling Drug. Legal documents
  - Bonn Treaty (as amended by Paris Protocol)
  - Budget. Notes and correspondence
  - Cartels. Printed articles and newspaper clippings; includes material relating to the cases of the Sterling Corporation, and I.G. Farbenindustrie, for which General Aniline and Film Corporation was allegedly a front (Box 15)
  - China. Printed articles
  - Constitution. Mimeograph copies of the By-Laws and Constitution of the Committee
  - Conventions, political. Printed article
  - Corporations. Printed articles and informational studies; includes material relating to German corporations
  - Cuba. Primarily newspaper articles and press releases relating to business investments and relations with Cuba
  - DEGO (German Gold Discount Bank)
  - Denmark. Relates to U.S. compensation to Denmark, 1957-1958
  - Drug films
  - Egypt. Articles on U.S. interests and aid to Egypt and Egyptian claims that the U.S. Trading with Enemy Act set a precedent for Egyptian confiscation of British and French property (Box 16)
  - Equivalence. Relates to compensation for confiscated assets
  - Farben, I. G., Farbenindustrie relationship to G.A.F. (See G.A.F. file below)
  - Foreign agents. Committee of Foreign Relations report concerned with covert operations such as lobbying; basic documents include bills to amend the Foreign Agents Registration Act
  - General Aniline and Film Corporation. Articles and basic documents relating to government seizure of the company during World War II under the Trading with Enemy Act, the company's subsequent operation under the supervision of the Alien Property Office of the U.S. Justice Department (which controls 97% of voting stock), a long ownership dispute between the Justice Department and the Swiss holding company Interhandel, and charges of political patronage under the Kennedy administration
  - General Aniline and Film Corporation. Articles and basic documents relating to government seizure of the company during World War II under the Trading with Enemy Act, the company's subsequent operation under the supervision of the Alien Property Office of the U.S. Justice Department (which controls 97% of voting stock), a long ownership dispute between the Justice Department and the Swiss holding company Interhandel, and charges of political patronage under the Kennedy administration (Box 17)
  - Germany. Primarily German newspaper clippings, articles, and German Embassy reports; English documents include an information sheet on the German General Law concerning the consequences of the war and Congressional Record excerpts
    - Advance payment
    - Bonds
    - Bundestag
    - Compensation loans
    - Dollar
    - East Zone
    - Foreign Aid Program
    - National debt
    - Reaction
    - Treaty
  - Guatemala. Articles, and State Department press releases (Box 18)
  - Hardship cases. Primarily correspondence; several specific cross-references to correspondence files including Dr. Harry Pfund's, which has a list of hardship cases (primarily charity organizations) by municipality
  - Hearings. Unpublished materials, 1956 July 18
  - Hundred Thousand Dollar Program. Material relating to a fund-raising campaign, ca. 1955 March
  - Indonesia
  - Investment. Statements, speeches, articles and a few basic documents on foreign economic policy, U.S. and foreign investments, and the Subcommittee on Foreign Economic Policy of the Joint Economic Committee of Congress
  - Investment
  - Japan. Articles, State Department press releases, and information from the Japanese Consulate General's Office; includes several documents related to the visit of Mamoru Shigemitsu (Foreign Minister), 1955 August 24-September 5
  - Lastenausgleich (Equalization of Burdens Law) (Box 19)
  - Lobby. Copies of quarterly lobby reports, statements of receipts, and an article relating to lobbying legislation, ca. 1960-1962
  - Liebernecht, Karl. Relates to government stock holdings, ca. 1958 February
  - Mailing lists. Committee members, 1957-1962
  - Miscellaneous. Articles, clippings and handwritten notes, presumably all by Executive Secretary James Finucane
  - Money. Articles relating to fund-raising
  - National Foreign Trade Convention. Report of the proceedings
  - Philippines. Basic documents
  - Poland. Press releases
  - Property. Printed articles
  - Prospectus. Newsletter
  - Proxy forms. Relates to general meeting of the Committee, 1962 December 11
  - Reparations. Notes and printed articles (Box 20)
  - Roechling. Printed articles relating to a reparation case
  - Schering. Printed articles and a letter relating to proposed legislation
  - Schuette. Correspondence, including the Studiengesellschaft fur Privatrechtliche Auslandinteressen e.V.
  - Carl Schurz Foundation (Memorial). Correspondence
  - Social Action Project. Christian Action and Community Service Committee project, 1958
  - Solicitations. Letters, and a German mailing list
  - Spur offering. Material relating to the purchase of government-owned stock in Spur Distributing Company, Inc.
  - Stinnes Corporation. Printed articles and other material relating to the purchase of the Hugo Stinnes Corporation
  - Studiengesellschaft fur Privatrechtliche Auslandsinteressen, e.V. Correspondence and publications (primarily in German) relating to confiscated property, and correspondence
  - Studiengesellschaft fur Privatrechtliche Auslandsinteressen, e.V. (Box 21)
  - Swiss
  - Tag Case. Relates to a U.S. Court of Appeals case, ca. 1959 May 21
  - Talk. Speech notes
  - Testimonials
  - Trading with enemy. Includes material relating to legislation
  - U.S. Bond Issue. Notes and other material, 1962 August 21
  - U.S. citizens. Includes a brief and a report by Kenneth S. Carlston, "Statement on the present position of American Citizens under the Trading with the Enemy Act," ca. 1956
  - U.S. government
    - Foreign Claims Settlement Commission Report
    - Justice Department
    - Office of Alien Property
  - U.S. wills. Includes a statement entitled, "Facts concerning the seizure of Strachwitz Trust by the Alien Property Custodian"
  - United Nations. Publications on human rights and a letter of protest from Chairman Libby to Secretary of State Dulles
  - War claims (Box 22)
  - Watches
  - Wiedergutmachung. Notes and newspaper articles (primarily in German) relating to reparations for war crimes
  - Windfall. Relates to U.S. custodianship of certain companies
  - World Court. Articles, and reports from the American Bar Association, and the International Law Association
  - Yalta. Clippings
- OFFICE FILE, 1953-1962 (Boxes 22-27)
  Minutes of meetings, press releases, position statements and reports, form letters, government documents, correspondence, notes, and printed matter. Arranged by subseries, as follows: minutes of meetings, press releases and position statements, government documents file, and pre-1955 file. The pre-1955 file contains the records of the Committee prior to 1955, including unarranged correspondence, notes, and printed matter.
  - Minutes of the annual meeting, 1954-1962 (Box 22)
  - Minutes of the executive committee, 1954-1962 (Box 23)
  - Press releases and position statements
    - Distribution sheets
    - Offering
    - Blue Service
    - Letter of Committee Dissolution, 1962
    - Release, 1962 April 12
    - Release, 1962 March 12
    - Fact sheets
    - Release, 1961 August 14
    - Letter to Editor, 1961 August 14
    - Scherzer testimony, 1961 August 2
    - Collier letter, 1961 July
    - Appeal letter and reprints, 1961 May 8
    - Problem paper release, 1961 February 23
    - Letter to Editor, 1961 January 13
    - Problem paper to President Kennedy, 1960
    - Statement by Bishop Hammaker at Republican Platform Committee, 1960 (Box 24)
    - Democratic Platform release, 1960
    - Scherzer statement, 1960 April
    - Church documents, 1960
    - Sheldon reply, 1960 March 11
    - Masaoka reprints, 1960 February 19
    - Annual meeting statement, 1960 February 9
    - Reply to Marquis Childs, 1960 January 20
    - Gerhard Testimony, 1959
    - Steuben Society statement, 1959
    - Statement by Bishop Hammaker, 1959
    - Notice of hearings, 1959 July
    - Hammaker testimony, 1959 June
    - Scherzer testimony, 1959 June
    - Statement on sale by Attorney General, 1959 March 15
    - Annual meeting resolutions, 1959 February 20
    - Libby letter on human rights, 1958 December 8
    - Letter enclosing booklet, 1958 August 13
    - Abolition of U.S. Office of Alien Property release, 1958 May 12
    - State Department release, 1958 March 29
    - Washington Post, 1958
    - Christian Herald, 1958
    - Quincy Wright, 1957
    - Norman Thomas, 1957
    - Collier, 1957
    - Letter to Eisenhower, 1957
    - Releases, 1954-1957
    - Releases other than newsletter, Vol. 1-3, 1953 November-1956 December
  - Government documents
    - Austrian State Treaty
    - Basic documents, pre- 1954 (Box 25)
    - Basic documents, 1954
    - Basic documents, 1955 (H.R. 6730)
    - Basic documents, 1955
    - Basic documents, 1956
    - Basic documents, 1956 (Johnston Bill, S-4 205)
    - Basic documents, German
    - Basic documents, 1957-1959
    - Basic documents, 1960
    - Basic documents, 1961
    - Bills, 1953-1956
    - Bills, 1957-1960
    - Bills, 1961 (H.R. 9463)
    - Bills, 1961 (H.R. 8305)
    - Bills, 1961 (H.R. 7479)
    - Bills, 1962 (H.R. 7283 and 5028) (Box 26)
    - Bills, 1962 (S. 2523, 2618, and 495)
    - Bonn Agreement
  - Pre- 1955 Files
  - Pre- 1955 Files (Box 27)
- NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS AND PRINTED MATTER, 1954-1962 (Boxes 28-33)
  Newspaper clippings concerning confiscated property, reactions to proposed legislation, activities of the Committee, and annotated printed material, consisting mainly of government publications. Arranged chronologically.
  - Clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 28)
  - Clippings, 1956
  - Clippings, 1956 (Aufbau)
  - Clippings, 1957 (Congressional Quarterly)
  - Clippings, 1957
  - Clippings, 1958-1959
  - Clippings, 1958-1959 (foreign language)
  - Clippings, (German papers)
  - Clippings, 1959-1960 (Congressional Quarterly)
  - Clippings, 1960
  - Clippings, 1960-1962 (foreign language) (Box 29)
  - Clippings, 1961-1962
  - Clippings, 1962
  - Clippings, extra
  - Clippings, duplicates for distribution
  - Scrapbook of clippings, testimonies, and literature circulated, 1959
  - Printed matter, annotated
    - Annual Report, U.S. Office of Alien Property, 1942-1952
    - Annual Report, U.S. Office of Alien Property, 1953-1958, 1961 (Box 30)
    - Congressional hearings and reports
    - Congressional hearings and reports (Box 31)
    - Congressional hearings and reports (Box 32)
    - Congressional hearings and reports (Box 33)
    - Miscellaneous reports and monographs